<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <particDesc>
           <listPerson>
              <person xml:id="jha">
                 <persName>Vineeta Jha</persName>
              </person>
              <person xml:id="coralynn">
                 <persName>Coralynn Davis</persName>
              </person>
              <person xml:id="translator" />
              <person xml:id="outsidelady">
              </person>
           </listPerson>
           
        </particDesc>
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div1 type="story">
            <head>
               <title>Dedh Bitna</title>
       <profileDesc>
        <particDesc>
           <listPerson>
              <person xml:id="jha">
                 <persName>Vineeta Jha</persName>
              </person>
              <person xml:id="coralynn">
                 <persName>Coralynn Davis</persName>
              </person>
              <person xml:id="translator" />
              <person xml:id="outsidelady">
              </person>
           </listPerson>
           
        </particDesc>
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
                 <persName type="storyteller" ref="#jha">Vineeta Jha</persName>
               <persName type="interviewer">Coralynn Davis</persName>
               <placeName>Vineeta's home</placeName>
               <date when-iso="2016-08-16"/> N/A by <persName>Dr. Coralynn V. Davis</persName>
               Line-by-line Transcription and Translation by Pranav Prakash </head>
            <div2 type="sp1">
               <sp who="#jha">
         <p>...सब के रक्षा करब, कुमाएर रहब त, हमरा ब्रह्मचारिणी बैन कॅ रक्षा करब । और ऊ ने भौ पाबेछेन, हुनकर अपनों रक्षा कैल ने भौ पाबेछेन । 
            …I will protect everyone, I will stay <objectName subtype="stateofbeing">virgin</objectName> then, I will become an <objectName subtype="stateofbeing">ascetic</objectName> and I will protect others. And that could not be realized, she was not even able to protect herself. </p>  
               </sp>
            </div2>
            
            <div2 type="sp2">
               <sp who="#translator">
            <p>[ So, this is about <objectName subtype="relationship">two sisters</objectName>… ]
            
            [ So, this is about <objectName subtype="relationship">two sisters</objectName>… ]</p>
               </sp>
            </div2>     
            
            <div2 type="sp1">
               <sp who="#jha">
                  <p>इ राजा...
            <persName subtype="person">This king</persName>… </p>
               </sp>
            </div2> 
            
            <div2 type="sp2">
               <sp who="#translator">
                <p>[ …one of them decides to… ]
            
            [ …one of them decides to… ]</p>
               </sp>
            </div2> 
            
            <div2 type="sp1">
               <sp who="#jha">
                  <p>हम कह देयछिये, आंहाँ कह देबै । 
            Let me finish <objectName subtype="adjective">narrating</objectName>, then you can explain to her. </p>
               </sp>
            </div2>      
            
            <div2 type="sp2">
               <sp who="#translator">
                  <p>[ …अच्छा ठीक छै । ]
            
            [ …ok, that’s fine… ]</p>
               </sp>
            </div2>   
            
            <div2 type="sp1">
               <sp who="#jha">
                  <p>राजा कुँवरदेव के दुटा बेटी छलखैन हँ । तऽ दुन्नू बेटी कॅ जहन पैग भेलेन, खेलैत देखलखिन । तऽ बिबाह लॅ, कहलखिन मन्त्री कॅ के बिबाह के योग बर खोज के लाबैला । 
            <persName>Rājā Kunwardev</persName> had <objectName subtype="relationship">two daughters</objectName>. When both <objectName subtype="relationship">daughters</objectName> had grown <objectName subtype="adjective">older</objectName>, he once saw them <objectName subtype="verb">playing</objectName>. Then, for their <objectName subtype="event">marriage</objectName>, he told his <persName type="person">minister</persName> to find a <persName type="person">suitable groom</persName> for their marriage. 
            
            तऽ हुन्कर छोटकी बेटी कहलखिन जे “नै, हम नै बिबाह करब । से हम तऽ कुमारी रैहकऽ सबक रक्षा करबै । बड़की बहिन कॅ बिबाह करा दियौ ।” 
            Then his <persName subtype="relationship">younger daughter</persName> said to him, “No, I do not want to get <objectName subtype="stateofbeing">married</objectName>. I will stay <objectName subtype="stateofbeing">unmarried</objectName> so that I may protect everyone. You proceed with the <objectName subtype="event">marriage</objectName> of my <perName type="relationship">elder sister</perName>.” 
            
            कहलखिन, “ठीक छै ।” 
             He replied, “Ok fine.”
            
            बड़की के बिबाह-दान करा देलखिन । हुनका बिदा कॅ देलखिन । उ सासुर गेलखिन । तखन कहैलखिन, “आहाँ जे हमरा लॅग में रॅहब, से तैसे तऽ आहाँ के नै तपस्या हैत ।” 
            The <persName subtype="relationship">elder daughter</persName> was married and given to her <persName subtype="relationship">husband</persName>. She was sent off to her <placeName>in-laws’ home</placeName>. She went to the<placeName> place of her in-laws</placeName>. Then <persName>the king</persName> said to his <persName type="relationship">younger daughter</persName>, “As long as you continue to live with me, you can’t immerse yourself in <objectName type="practice">spiritual austerities</objectName>.”  
            
            कहलखिन, “हम जंगल में जाएब, तपस्या करब, तपस्वी बनब, आ सब के रक्षा करबै ।” त हुनका राजा रानी कहलखिन जे, “ठीक छै ।” ओ अपन...राजसी वस्त्र त्याग कॅ, गेरूआँ वस्त्र धारण कॅ क, आ एकटा हुनका साथ में खवासनी दॅ देलखिन, और जे किछु हुन्कर, छोट-मोट सामग्री दॅ देलखिन, जे, “जाऊ आब, आहाँ जे जंगल जायब, से जाऊ - की करब हम? - आहाँ जहन बिबाह ने करब त ।”
             She replied, “I will go to the <placeName subtype="woods">forest</placeName>, I will do <objectName subtype="practice">spiritual austerities</objectName>, I will become an <objectName subtype="stateofbeing">ascetic</objectName>, and I will protect everyone.” Then <persName subtype="relationship">the king</persName> and <persName subtype="relationship">the queen</persName> replied, “All right.”  She gave up her…<objectName subtype="cloth">royal clothing</objectName>, she wore an <objectName>ascetic’s robe</objectName>, and a <objectName subtype="relationship">female caretaker</objectName> was asked to <objectName subtype="verb">accompany</objectName> her to the <placeName>forest</placeName>. And whatever little things belonged to her, all were given to her. And they said to her, “Now you may leave, you who wish to go to the <placeName>forest</placeName>, you may proceed – what can we possibly do? – now that you don’t want to get <objectName subtype="stateofbeing">married</objectName>.”
            
            जाएत-जाएत एकटा जंगल में गेलखिन उ । ओय जंगल में, बहूत पैग जंगल छलै, अ ओय में एकटा कुटिया बना देलखिन, ओय में रहै छलैथऽ, दासी हुन्कर सेवा करे छलेन्हऽ, अ उ रहैथ । एक दिन कि भेलै, त एकटा साधू एलखिन, भगवान के रूप धॅ क । साधू एलखिन, भिक्षा माँगेय लॅ । 
            She kept walking until she arrived at a <placeName>forest</placeName>. In that forest – it was a very <placeName >large forest</placeName> – in that forest, she built a <objectName subtype="placetolive">shelter</objectName>, and she began living in there. <persName subtype="occupation">Her personal attendant</persName> took care of her, and she lived there. One day, it so happened that a <persName>sage</persName> arrived there, in the <objectName>guise of a god</objectName>. A sage came there, begging for <objectName>alms</objectName>. 
            
            [ भगवान एलखिन साधू के रूप धॅ क । ]
            [ <persName>A god</persName> arrived there in the <persName>guise of a sage</persName>.]
            
            साधू के रूप धॅ क, भगवान एलखिन भिक्षा माँगेल । हुनका भिक्षा दॅ देलखिन, अ उ जाय छलखिन्ह जे साधू, त गाछ पर छलैह कऊआ बैसल, उ कऊआ हुन्का लैट्रिन कॅ देलकन, साधू के ऊपर । उ साधू कहलखिन्ह, तपस्या हुन्कर जाँच करै के लेल आयल रहथिन, तॅ ओ लैट्रिन कॅ देल्केन, ओ जाय काल में ओकरा श्राप दॅ देलखिन, “जे जाह, ए जंगल में आग लाएग जेतो, तू मर जेब ।”
            In the guise of a sage, <persName>a god</persName> came there seeking <objectName subtype="food">some alms</objectName>. She gave <objectName subtype="food">alms</objectName> to him, and he went on his way. Then, there was <objectName subtype="bird">a crow</objectName> sitting on a tree. <objectName subtype="bird">That crow</objectName> shat on the <persName>sage</persName>, its droppings fell on the sage. That sage said – he had been there to test her <objectName subtype="practice">spiritual austerities</objectName>, but the <objectName subtype="bird">crow</objectName> shat on him – that sage cursed <objectName subtype="bird">the crow</objectName>, as he was about to leave the <placeName>forest</placeName>, he put a <objectName subtype="idea">curse</objectName> on him, ”Be gone, there will a <objectName>fire</objectName> in the <placeName>forest</placeName>, and you will <objectName subtype="stateofbeing">die</objectName>.”
            
            The video snaps between 2:01 and 2:02 minutes, it seems a portion of recording here was corrupted. 
            
            भिक्षा देयछे । कॅल जोड़ेलखिन जे, “की आज्ञा ? कहूँ ।” त उ कहलखिन, “किछु ने, तपस्वी के जंगल में आग लाग गेलेय, जदि आहाँ कॅ शक्ति य त बुझा दियौ, नै तऽ, आहाँ के बहिन नै जीत, जड़ जायत, ज़िन्दा ने रहत, जड़ जायत ।”
            It gave <objectName subtype="food">alms</objectName> to her. With <objectName>folded hands</objectName>, she said, “What is your command? Tell it to me.” It replied, “Nothing much, the <placeName>forest</placeName> of the <objectName>female ascetic</objectName> has caught <objectName>fire</objectName>, if you are mighty enough, please <objectName subtype="idea">extinguish the fire</objectName>, otherwise, <persName subtype="relationship">your sister</persName> won’t survive, she will get <objectName subtype="stateofbeing">burnt</objectName>, she won’t be <objectName subtype="state">alive</objectName>, she will be <objectName subtype="idea">burnt to death</objectName>.” 
            
            कहलखिन, “से बात छै ?” 
            तऽ “हाँ ।”  
            तऽ “ओऽ तऽ हम दू मिनट में विष्णु भगवान काबू कॅ लेबेन ।” 
            तऽ “केना ?”
            
            She said, “Is that so?”
            To which it replied “Yes”
            Then she said, “I see, then I can control <persName subtype="god">Viṣṇu</persName> in two minutes.”
            Then it queries, “How so?”
            
            “ओ ब्रह्मचारिणी बनली तपस्वी...से...हुनका से ने भेलेन । कुमारब्रता रहली त, आहाँ पतिब्रता भो कॅ से इ जंगल के मिझा लेब ?”
            त कहलखिन - “हँ । हम मिझा देबै । बहिन के रक्षा हम एत्ते से करब ।”
            “That ‘<persName subtype="description">female renunciant-turned-ascetic</persName>’…she…she could not do it. She was a <objectName subtype="stateofbeing">virgin ascetic</objectName>, but you are <objectName subtype="stateofbeing">married women</objectName>, will you be able to <objectName subtype="idea">extinguish the forest fire</objectName>? 
            She replied, “Yes, I will put it out. I will protect <persName subtype="relationship">my sister</persName> from here itself.”
            
            The video snaps again between 2:35 and 2:36. 
            
            “इ आहाँ रक्षा करूँ । तुलसी में उ जल देलखिन, ओहिते जंगल के आग मिझा गेले ।” 
            “This you should protect. As soon as she poured <objectName>water</objectName> on the <objectName>tulsī plant</objectName>, the <objectName>forest fire</objectName> was put out.” 
            
            तहन बहिन के आब कॅ कहैछथिन जे, “देखियो, आहाँ माता पिता के ठुकरा देलियेन जे ‘हम ने करब बिबाह । हम सबक रक्षा करब ।’ और आहाँ के अपन रक्षा कैल ने भेल । आहाँ जे जंगल में रहलों ओय जंगल में आहाँ के लैग कॅ कतैक जीब - जन्तु जड़ गेलै । तैं इ जरूरी नै छे जे, ‘आहाँ कुमारी रहब, तखने आहाँ रक्षा कॅ सकैछिये, ब्रह्मचारिणी बन कॅ ।’ अहाँ परिबारिक गृहस्थियो में रह के सबके रक्षा कॅ सकेछिये ।” 
            Then she went to <persName subtype="relationship">her sister</persName> and said to her, “See, you <persName subtype="relationship">disregarded mother and father</persName> as you declared, ‘I will not marry. I will protect everyone.’  And you could not even save yourself. <placeName>In the forest</placeName> where you were residing, how many beings – <objectName>animals and plants</objectName> – in your <objectName>vicinity</objectName> were burnt to death! So, it isn't necessarily the case that ‘you protect others only when you are <objectName subtype="stateofbeing">unmarried</objectName>, only when you are a <objectName subtype="idea">renunciant</objectName>.’ You can protect others even when you lead the <objectName subtype="idea">life of a householder</objectName>.” </p></sp>
            </div2>
         </pers>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
