<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <particDesc>
           <listPerson>
              <person xml:id="jha">
                 <persName>Vineeta Jha</persName>
              </person>
              <person xml:id="coralynn">
                 <persName>Coralynn Davis</persName>
              </person>
              <person xml:id="translator" />
              <person xml:id="outsidelady">
              </person>
           </listPerson>
           
        </particDesc>
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 type="story">
            <head>
               <title>Dedh Bitna</title>
               <persName type="storyteller" ref="#jha">Vineeta Jha</persName>
               <persName type="interviewer">Coralynn Davis</persName>
               <placeName>Vineeta's home</placeName>
               <date when-iso="2016-09-08"/> Maithili Folklore 1 Documented by <persName>Dr. Coralynn V. Davis</persName>
               Line-by-line Transcription and Translation by Pranav Prakash </head>
            <div2 type="sp1">
               <sp who="#jha">
                  <p>एकटा प'रवार म+, एकटा बे/टयो-ला बहू
                     
                     त रहेछे तप8या जे एकटा बे/टयो ने होयेछे । आर बेट= पर
                     
                     . . . सास कॅ अपन बेट= बहु
                     
                     त सCुदर लागेछे, और पतू ोहुके बेट= बहू
                     
                     त खराब लागेछे ।
                     
                     In a <objectName type="relationship">family</objectName>, for the sake of having a <objectName>child</objectName> – even if one were to have a <objectName>girl</objectName> – a <objectName>family</objectName> has
                     to go through a lot. One needs to do a lot of penance for bringing up even a <objectName>girl child</objectName>. With regard to <objectName type="relationship">daughters</objectName>...a <objectName type="relationship">mother-in-law</objectName> immensely adores her pretty <objectName>daughter</objectName>, but she
                     intensely abhors her <objectName type="relationship">daughter-in-law</objectName>.
                     
                     ओए पर छे . . . जेहमरा सबके जीवछ नद= छै । औतऽ /हनका घर म+ बे...बाल-बMचा ने होयेछलन
                     रहे त पतू ोहुके कमला-जी के पजू ा करवैछOथन - जीवछ मैया के - तऽ जीवछ मैया आशीवाRद देय छOथन
                     । तऽ ऊ गभRवती होयेछे । तो ओकरा बMचा होयेछे ।
                     
                     In that context...so, we have a <placeName>river</placeName> called <placeName type="river">Jīvach</placeName>. There, in their <placeName>house</placeName>...she was unable
                     to give birth to a <objectName>child</objectName>, so the <objectName type="relationaship">mother-in-law</objectName> made her <objectName type="relationship">daughter-in-law worship</objectName> the Goddess
                     <persName type="goddess">Kamalā</persName> – the goddess of the <placeName type="river">River Jīvach</placeName> – then, <persName>Mother Jīvach</persName> gave a blessing to her. She became pregnant. Then a <objectName type="human">child</objectName> was born to her.
                     
                     ओकरा घर म+ एकटा गाय पालल रहे । ओय गाय-यो कॅ बUछया होयेछे । एकरो बMचा होयेछे आ
                     गाय-ओ कॅ बUछया होयेछे । धीरे-धीरे ओ बMचा के पैग होयेछे ।
                     
                     A <objectName type="animal">cow</objectName> was being tended in her <placeName>house</placeName>. She too gave birth to a female <placeName type="animal">calf</placeName>. The
                     <objectName type="relation">daughter-in-law</objectName> had a girl <objectName type="human">child</objectName>, the <objectName>cow</objectName> too had a female <objectName type="animal">calf</objectName>. That <objectName type="human">child</objectName> was gradually
                     growing up.
                     
                     ओकरा खाय ल देयछे । गभRवती रहेछे त फल-फूल-सब । खबू ओकरा मान-दान होयेछे । ओकरा
                     घर म+ बेट= होयेछे । त ओकरा...ओकर दाद= ओकरा खबू सCुदर सामान आदर करेछे - ओय बMचा के ।
                     रखेछे दादा दाद=, खबू घमू ाबे-Xफराबेछे । ओय गाय के बाछY होयेछे, त ओकरो खाय ल भेटैछे ।
                     
                     They fed her. Since she was pregnant, they gave her <objectName type="food">fruits</objectName> and <objectName>delicacies</objectName>. They
                     respected her, and they took good care of her. A <objectName type="human">girl child</objectName> was born in her <placeName>home</placeName>. To her...her
                     <objectName type="relationship">grandmother</objectName> treated her – the <objectName type="human">girl child</objectName> – with much affection and respect. Their <objectName type="relationship">grandfather</objectName>
                     and <objectName type="relationship">grandmother</objectName> took care of her. They traveled and played together a lot. That <objectName type="animal">cow</objectName> who gave
                     birth to a female <objectName type="animal">calf</objectName>, her <objectName type="animal">calf</objectName> too was fed properly.
                     
                     जहन उ पगै भो जायेछे, घमू छै े - खेलैछे, पैग होयेछे, त ओकर बाबा कहेछे Xक एकरा आब...आब
                     [बबाह के लेल बर खोजल जाय । तो ओकरा [बबाह होयेछे । [बबाह होयेछे । [बबाह होयेछे, दरुांगमन
                     होयेछे, त ओकरा उ बUछया दॅ देल जायेछे । ओकरा संगे जे गाय के बMचा भेल रहे, उ...पैग बाछY भो
                     जायेछे, उहो ओकरा दो देल जायेछे...जे “इ हमर पोती भेल, तओ ओकरा बाछY भेल, उ पोती के हम देब ।”
                     दॅ देयछे ।
                     
                     When she grew older, she used to roam around and play some <objectName>sports</objectName>. When she was grown, then her <objectName type="relationship">grandfather</objectName> said that now...now they should search a <objectName type="relationship">groom</objectName> for her <objectName>marriage</objectName>. Then she was wed. Her <objectName type="event">wedding</objectName> took place. Her <objectName type="event">wedding ceremony</objectName> was completed, she
                     was given to her husband, and she was gifted with a female calf. This calf was the one who was
                     born at the same time when she was herself born, that <objectName type="animal">calf</objectName>...that <objectName type="animal">calf</objectName> too was grown up, and
                     her <objectName type="relationship">grandfather</objectName> gifted the <objectName type="animal">calf</objectName> to her...on the pretext that ”when my <objectName type="relationship">granddaughter</objectName> was born,
                     my <objectName type="animal">cow</objectName> too had a <objectName type="animal">calf</objectName>, and I will give the <objectName type="animal">calf</objectName> to my <objectName type="relationship">granddaughter</objectName>.” He gave the <objectName type="animal">calf</objectName> to her.
                     
                     सासरु जायेछे, खबू सCुदर, खशु ी रहेछे । जखन खशु ी से रहे चलछै े, ओ लड़कa रOधया गभवR ती
                     होयेछे । ओ जे गभRवती होयेछे, आ बUछया, सेहो ओकर रहेछे गभRवती ।
                     
                     She went to the <placeName>home</placeName> of her in-laws. It was all nice and good, and everyone was glad.
                     When everything was going on well, then that girl, <persName>Rādhiyā</persName>, became pregnant. When she
                     became pregnant, her <objectName type="animal">calf</objectName>, she too became pregnant.
                     
                     तऽ ओकरा बेट= होयेछे। त ओकर सास मँहु घमु ा के चल जायछे, देख कॅ, “एह, बेट=-ये भेलै । एह
                     बेट=-ये छे ।”
                     
                     Then a <objectName type="human">girl</objectName> was born to her. Her <objectName type="relationship">mother-in-law</objectName> turned her face away and she walked off.
                     After seeing her <objectName type="human">new-born girl</objectName>, she said, “Alas, a <objectName type="human">girl</objectName> is after all born. What a shame, this <objectName type="human">child</objectName>
                     is <objectName type="gender">girl</objectName>!”
                     
                     त कहेछे दोसर, “है, एना Xकया करैछY ?”
                     
                     Others responded to her, “Hey, why are you behaving in this way?”
                     
                     पड़ोस के लोग, “बेट= छै त कa छै, सCुदर बdड-य, रहॅ /दयौ, अपन करम भाग छै ।” बेट= कॅ देख
                     कॅ चल जायेछे ।
                     
                     Her <objectName>neighbors</objectName> said, “How does it matter that the <objectName type="human">child</objectName> is a <objectName type="gender">girl</objectName>? She is very beautiful. Let
                     her be what she is. Everyone comes with their <objectName>apportioned fate</objectName>.” They saw the <objectName type="gender">girl</objectName>, and they
                     went away.
                     
                     ओय गाय कॅ बाछY होयेछे, ओकरा खबू सCुदर स काड़ी कपड़ा लपेट क गदRन म+ बाँधल जायेछे, जे
                     गाय के ने नज़र लागे । “हमर बेट= के कोनो मोल नै । गाय के नै नज़र लागे, गाय-यो क बाँधल जायेछे,
                     अ ओकरा बMचो क बाँधल जायेछे, काड़ी कपड़ा, गला म+ ।”
                     
                     A female <objectName type="animal">calf</objectName> was born to the <objectName type="animal">cow</objectName>. A female <objectName type="animal">calf</objectName> was born to the <objectName type="animal">cow</objectName>. She was dressed
                     beautifully, and a <objectName>black cloth</objectName> was tied to her <placeName type="partofbody">neck</placeName> so that she might be protected from <objectName>evil eye</objectName>.
                     The <objectName type="relationship">daughter-in-law</objectName> wondered, “My <objectName type="relationship">daughter</objectName> has no worth for my in-laws. So that the <objectName type="animal">cow</objectName> not suffer from <objectName>evil eye</objectName>, they tied a <objectName>black cloth</objectName> to the cow too, and they tied it to her calf too, a black cloth, in her neck.”
                     
                     ओकर बMचा जे बीमार रहेछे, संजोग छै, ओकरा बMचा क खबू तजे बखु ार भौ जायेछे । रOधया
                     बMचा के तजे बखु ार भौ जायेछे । त ओकर सास के कहेछे, “बdड बखु ार छे, देhखयो नऽ ।”
                     
                     Her <objectName type="relationship">daughter</objectName> fell ill – as chance would have it – her <objectName type="human">child</objectName> suffered from high fever.
                     <objectName type="relationship">Radhiyā’s daughter</objectName> had high fever. She told her <objectName type="mother">mother-in-law</objectName>, “She has <objectName type="condition">high fever</objectName>, please take a look at her.”
                     
                     “है, हमर अपने गाय के बMचा बीमार ए ।” मढ़ु = झाँएठ कॅ चल जायेछे । “हम ने एखन देखबै ।
                     हमर अपने गाय के बMचा बीमार ए ।”
                     
                     Her <objectName type="relationship">mother-in-law</objectName> said, “Go away, the <objectName type="human">child</objectName> of my <objectName type="animal">cow</objectName> is sick as well.” She tossed her
                     <objectName type="partofbody">head</objectName> in disgust, and she went away. Her <objectName type="relationship">mother-in-law</objectName> declared, “I won’t see your <objectName type="gender">girl</objectName> now,
                     my <objectName type="animal">cow’s child </objectName>itself is sick.”
                     
                     इ अपने तलु सी के रस, lडबीया जड़ा के, तखन अपन बMचा कॅ दॅ रहल छै । गाय के बMचा, सेहो
                     बीमार भौ जायेछे । त गाय के बMचा ले, गाय OचOचया रहल छै । कान रहल छै । “इ कान रहल छै, त
                     एकरा मढ़ु = घमु ा क जा रहल छै ।” “हमरा स...टाईम नै य...हमर गाय के बMचा बीमार य ।” गाय के बMचा बीमार छै, त अपने कान रहल छै । ओकरा गदRन...डॉoटर सब पकड़ क गदRन म+ कपड़ा लगबैछै जे नजऱ नैलागे, और डॉoटर सब इCजेoशन लगबैछे जे मरै न इ गाय के बMचा । फे र पोती के छोड़ क चल जायेछे । तखन इ रOधया कहेछे जे “हे भगवान, अगला जनम हमरो गाय-ए बनायेब ।”
                     
                     She got the <objectName>juice</objectName> of the <objectName type="plant">tulsī</objectName> plant, she lit an earthen lamp, then she gave the juice to
                     her <objectName type="relationship">daughter</objectName>. The <objectName type="animal">cow’s child </objectName>– it too had fallen sick. So, the <objectName type="animal">cow</objectName> was howling for her <objectName type="animal">child</objectName>. She was crying. The <objectName type="relationship">daughter-in-law</objectName> noticed, “My <objectName type="human">girl</objectName> too is weeping, but my <objectName type="relationship">mother-in-law</objectName> turns
                     her <objectName type="bodypart">face</objectName> away from her.” Her <objectName type="relationship">mother-in-law</objectName> said to her, “I don’t have...I don’t have time...my <objectName type="animal">cow’s child</objectName> is sick.” Since the <objectName type="animal">cow’s child</objectName> was sick, she was crying. The <objectName>doctors</objectName> held her neck...her <objectName type="bodypart">neck</objectName>, and they put a <objectName>cloth</objectName> around her <objectName type="bodypart">neck</objectName> so that she could be saved from <objectName>evil eyes</objectName>, and the <objectName type="human">doctors</objectName> gave an <objectName>injection</objectName> to the <objectName type="animal">cow’s child</objectName>. The <objectName type="relationship">mother-in-law</objectName> again left their <placeName>room</placeName> without paying any attention to her <objectName type="relationship">granddaughter</objectName>. Then <persName>Radhiyā</persName> prayed, “O God, in the next birth, please do make me a <objectName type="animal">cow</objectName>.”
                     
                     पजू ा करेछन भगवान स ।
                     
                     She prayed to the <objectName>God</objectName>.
                     
                     [ गाय के जीवन हमरा से बेसी नीक छै । ]
                     
                     [ The life of a <objectName type="animal">cow</objectName> is much better than my life. ]
                     
                     “बेसी नीक छै एकटा गाय के जीवन हमरा स ।” जे, “ओकर बMचा लॅ कान रहलछे, ओकरा दवाइ
                     पर दवाइ पड़ रहल छै । ओकरा गदRन म+ नज़र नैलागे से काड़ी कपड़ा बनहा रहल छै । और हमर बMचा
                     बीमार य, त कहेय, ‘एखन ने देखबो ।’ आय जे हमहूगाय रहतs, तखन फaल होयेछे जे हम औरत छYये
                     ताँय हमर बMचा कॅ ने देखेय । आय जे हम जानवर रहतs, गाय रहतs, त हमर बMचा के त एहना इलाज
                     होइते । डॉoटर लग लै जायल जेते, सईुया लगवाएल जेते ।” तtकहेछे, “हे भगवान, अगला जनम हमरो
                     गाये बनायब ।”
                     
                     A <objectName type="animal">cow</objectName> is much better off than I am in my life. She said, “My <objectName type="relationship">mother-in-law</objectName> cries for the
                     <objectName type="animal">cow’s child</objectName>, and the <objectName type="animal">calf</objectName> is given all kinds of <objectName>medicine</objectName>. So that <objectName>evil eye</objectName> not be not cast on her <objectName type="animal">calf</objectName>, they are preparing a <objectName>black cloth</objectName> for her. And my <objectName type="relationship">daughter</objectName> is sick, she says, ‘I won’t be able to see her now.’ If only I were a <objectName type="animal">cow</objectName> today! At such moments, one feels it, since I am <objectName type="human">women</objectName>, no
                     one pays attention to my <objectName type="human">child</objectName>. If I were an <objectName>animal</objectName>, if I were a <objectName type="animal">cow</objectName>, then my child too would have
                     received proper medical attention. They would take her to the <objectName type="professio ">doctor</objectName>, they would give her a shot.” That’s why she prayed, “O God, please make me too a <objectName type="animal">cow</objectName> in the next birth.”
                  </p></sp>
            </div2>
            
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>

