<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <head>Maithili Folklore 16_09_08_a_2
            Documented by Dr. Coralynn V. Davis
            Transcription and Translation by Pranav Prakash
            <persName type="storyteller" ref="$#nibha">Nibha Kumari</persName>
            <persName type="interviewer"> Coralynn V. Davis</persName>
            <placeName>Mai Madhubani</placeName>
            <date when-iso="2016-09-08"></date>
         </head>
         <div1 type="sp1">
            <sp who="#jha">
            <p> एकटा <objectName type="human">लड़का</objectName> रॅहैछे, जेकर शादी होयेछे । उ अपन शादी होयेछे, नऽ, त बड खुश रहैछे, जे हमर शादी भैले ।
            
            There is a <objectName type="human">lad</objectName> who gets married. He is very pleased with his marriage – “My marriage has
            happened.”
            
            ओ...ओ <objectName type="trait">खुशी</objectName> में नऽ अपन सासुर जायेछे, तो ओकर सासुर में नऽ, सब ओते <objectName type="trait">अमीर</objectName> नै रहैछे, कनि <objectName type="trait">गरीब</objectName> टाईप के
            रहैछे, तऽ ओकर सास न <objectName type="food">खिचड़ी</objectName> बनाबैछै । जो...जे में नऽ दैल, आलू-ऊलू, सब कुछ दॅ कऽ बनबेछै, उ टेस्टी रॅहैछे,
            ओकरा वैह खा ल दैछे, एक साइद में <objectName type="food">खिचड़ी</objectName> रॅहैछे और एकटा कटौरी में भैड़ कऽ <objectName type="food">घी</objectName> दॅ दे छै ।
            
            He…he is so <objectName type="trait">happy</objectName> that he pays a visit to his wife’s family in their <placeName>village</placeName>. But his in-laws are not
            very <objectName type="trait">rich</objectName>, they are like <objectName type="trait">poor</objectName> families, so his mother-in-law decides to cook <objectName type="food">khicadī</objectName> for him. It is
            …it is made up of <objectName type="food">lentils</objectName>, <objectName type="food">potato</objectName> and the like; everything is mixed together, and it is <objectName type="trait">tasty</objectName>. She
            serves this <objectName>dish</objectName> to him, she puts <objectName type="food">khicaḍī</objectName> on one side, and she gives him a bowl full of <objectName type="food">ghee</objectName>.
           
            तऽ ओ खायेछे नऽ, <objectName type="food">घी</objectName> और <objectName type="food">खिचड़ी</objectName> दुनु मिला कै, त ओकरा बहुत सुन्दर लागेछे ।
            
            When he eats it, by mixing <objectName type="food">ghee</objectName> and <objectName type="food">khicadī</objectName> together, he absolutely loves it.
            
            त अपन <persName type="relation">सास</persName> स पुछैछे जे इ की बनैलियेयऽ, त कहेछे - “बउआ, किछ न बनैलिये, हमरा घर में किच्छो न छले,
            <objectName type="food">खिचड़ी</objectName> बना लेलिये, <objectName type="food">घी</objectName> दौ देलों हँ ।” कहलके - “नै, <persName type="relation">माँ</persName>, बड सुन्दर छलै, हमरा बड नीक लागल है । अहाँ के बेटी
            क आबे यऽ न?” त कहलके - “हाँ, आबे यऽ ।” त कहलके - “ठीक छै ।”
            
            He asks his <persName type="relation">mother-in-law</persName> – “What have you cooked for me?” She replies – “<objectName type="human">Son</objectName>, I have cooked
            nothing really, there was nothing left in my house, so I cooked <objectName type="food">khicaḍī</objectName> for you, and poured some
            <objectName type="food">ghee</objectName> over it.” He replies – “Not at all, <persName type="mother">Ma</persName>, this is truly delicious, I liked it very much. Does your
            daughter know the recipe of this dish?” She answers – “Yes, she does.” He responds – “That’s
            great.”
            
            तकरा बाद, ओ <objectName type="time">रॉत</objectName> भेलै, फेर ओ अपन...<objectName type="time">सुबह</objectName> मे...जहन प्रात भो गैले नऽ, तखन उ अपन आबेत रह, <placeName>रस्ता</placeName> में नऽ
            उ सोचैत रेहे जे अपन <placeName>घॅर</placeName> जेबै अपन कन्या के कहबै <objectName type="food">खिचड़ी</objectName> बनाबै ल, तऽ “<objectName type="food">खिचड़ी</objectName>-<objectName type="food">खिचड़ी</objectName>” कहत कहत नऽ
            ओकरा “<objectName type="food">खिरचिड़ी</objectName>-<objectName type="food">खिरचिड़ी</objectName>” कहाय छलै यऽ ।
            
            Afterwards, the <objectName type="time">night</objectName> descends, and then he…in the <objectName type="time">morning</objectName>…when it is <objectName type="time">dawn</objectName>, he starts his
            return journey. On the <placeName>road</placeName>, he decides he would ask his wife to cook <objectName type="food">khicaḍī</objectName> as soon as he
            reaches <placeName>home</placeName>. He begins repeating the name, “<objectName type="food">khicadī</objectName> – <objectName type="food">khicadī</objectName>,“ so as to commit it to his
            memory, but, by a slip of tongue, he ends up saying “<objectName type="food">khirciḍī</objectName> – <objectName type="food">khirciḍī</objectName>” over and over again.
            
            तऽ <placeName>रस्ता</placeName> में एकटा बनजारन रॅहैछे जे <objectName type="animal">चिड़िया</objectName>...उर...पकड़ेत रॅहैछै, तऽ ओ बैजते जात रहै “खिरचिड़ी-खिरचिड़ी”,
            उकरा “खिचड़ी-खिचड़ी” कहैत कहैत “<objectName type="food">खिरचिड़ी</objectName>-<objectName type="food">खिरचिड़ी</objectName>” कहा जायेत रहैछे । बनजारन जे सुनैछै नऽ, तऽ सब
            उकरा सुनाय दैछे जे, सऽ कहैछै “<objectName type="food">खिरचड़ी</objectName>” यानि “उड़ चिड़ी” उकरा सुनाय देछै । तो बनजारन के बहूते गुस्सा
            आबेछै जे हम चिड़िया फसाबै छी, आर इ कहैछे “उड़ चिड़ी - उड़ चिड़ी” यानि “सबटा चिड़िया उड़ जो” । त
            ओकरा...उ बनजारन नऽ पकड़ क खूब पीटैयऽ, जे “खीरचिड़ी” न कही, “आते-जा-फसते-जा” से कही ।
            
            So, there is a gypsy <objectName type="human">woman</objectName> somewhere on his way, and she is trying to catch…catch <objectName type="animal">birds</objectName>.
            Meanwhile, he is uttering “<objectName type="food">khircidī</objectName> – <objectName type="food">khircidī</objectName>”, as he has confused the pronouciation of “<objectName type="food">khicadī</objectName> –
            <objectName type="food">khicaḍī</objectName>” with “khircidī – khircidī”. When the gypsy woman hears his utterance – and she is able
            to listen fully to his speech – she reckons he is indeed saying “khircidī”, meaning “fly away, bird
            – fly away, bird!” She is furious with <objectName type="trait">anger</objectName>. On one hand, she is trying to catch the <objectName type="bird">bird</objectName>, and, on
            the other hand, he is telling them – “fly away, <objectName type="bird">bird</objectName> – fly away, <objectName type="bird">bird</objectName>!” It implies he wishes “all birds
            should fly away.” That gypsy woman grabs…him, and smacks the hell out of him. “Do not say
            “khirciḍī”, rather say “come-on-get-ensnared!”,” she tells him.
            
            तहन, आगाँ गैले...फेर ओ...याद कॅ लेलके “आगे-जा-फसते-जा”, उकरा याद एलै जे ओ खिचड़ी के नाम छै “आते-
            जा-फसते-जा” ।
            
            Afterwards, he resumes his journey…again he…he memorizes the expression “come-on-get-
            ensnared!” He believes that the original name of <objectName type="food">khicadī</objectName> is “come-on-get-ensnared!”
            
            तऽ फेर आगे जा क ओकरा एकटा आदमी भेटै छ, जेतै शादी होइत रॅहैछै...ओकरा कुछ बिबाद...बिबाद के कारण
            नऽ...ओकरा लड़का के, मतलब दहेज के कारण, लड़की के बाप के पैइसा ने रॅहैछे, तेक्कै कारण...ओकरा...मतलब,
            पुलिसवला-सब आब जायछै ओत्त, त उ बाजेत रॅहैछे छ “आते-जा-फसते-जा”, “आते-जा-फसते-जा” । ओत्तै नऽ,
            लड़की के बाप क बड खराब...अथि...लड़का के बाप क खराब लागेछै जे हमर बेटा एक त जेल जा रहलयऽ, उपर से
            कहैछ “आते-जा-फसते-जा”...ओत्ते जा क नऽ, दुनु फैमिली-वला पकैड़ के ओकरा खूब पीटैछे, जे कही “एसा-रोज-
            रोज-हो” ।
            
            As he saunters ahead, he comes across a <objectName type="human">man</objectName> whose marriage was about to take place…but a
            conflicting issue had come to fore…because of a feud…a feud concerning his marriage, that is,
            because of his <objectName>dowry</objectName>; the bride’s father did not have enough <objectName>money</objectName> to pay for his daughter’s
            <objectName>dowry</objectName>, that is why…to arrest the groom…, that is, a group of <objectName type="job">policemen</objectName> arrive on the scene,
            while he is repeating “come-on-get-ensnared”, “come-on-get-ensnared.” So then, the bride’s
            father felt very bad…eh…the groom’s father felt miserable that his son is being put in the <placeName>jail</placeName>,
            and this lad is cheekily saying – “come-on-get-ensnared”…So then, both groom’s and bride’s
            family catch hold of him and spank him savagely. Then they advise him to say – “may-it-
            happen-everyday.”
            
            तो ओ फेर याद कै ले छै “एसा-रोज-रोज-हो” जे हमरा मार ने खाय के यऽ ।
            
            So, he thinks, “I do not want to get hit again”, and he memorizes the expression “may-it-happen-
            everyday.”
            
            फेर आगा जाय छे त देखैछे एकटा नव-युवक मर गेल रहै छै । ओकर <objectName>लाश</objectName> लौ...क जायेछै । तऽ ओ, <objectName type="human">मतलब</objectName>,
            आदमी सब दुख भौ क, ओकरा जड़बै लॅ जायछै । तऽ ओ कहैत रॅहैछे “एसा-रोज-रोज-हो”, “एसा-रोज-रोज-
            हो”...ओकर...ओ <objectName>मुर्दा</objectName> क रैख दै छै नीचाँ म, कहैछे कि...ओकरा खूब पीटैछे...जे कही “ऐसा-कभी-न-हो”, “ऐसा-
            कभी-न-हो” । तेक्के बाद फिर, मतलब, उ रटै लागेछै, फेर आगाँ जायेछे ।
            
            On his journey ahead, he arrives at place where a youth has died. His <objectName>corpse</objectName> is…being carried
            by his <objectName type="human">kinsmen</objectName> who are mourning his death and moving his <objectName>dead body</objectName> to the <placeName>funeral pyre</placeName>.
            Meanwhile, this lad is repeating – “may-it-happen-everyday”, “may-it-happen-everyday”…they
            keep his…his <objectName>dead body</objectName> on the floor, and they say…they beat him up very badly…they tell him
            to repeat “may-this-never-happen”, “may-this-never-happen”. Thereafter, as one may infer, he
            restarts memorizing this expression by rote, and he resumes his onward journey.
            
            तऽ फेर एकटा <objectName type="human">आदमी</objectName> नऽ...<placeName>खेत</placeName> में काम करैत रॅहैछे, आ ओकरा खूब <placeName>खेत</placeName> में उपजल रॅहैछे, तेकरा फेर
            ओ...ओ मात्र बाजैत रहै जे “ऐसा-कभी-न-हो”, “ऐसा-कभी-न-हो” । तऽ मतलब...उ...जहन उ <placeName>खेत</placeName> में काम
            करत रहै छै, त ओकरा सुनाय दे छै जे उ आदमी बाजय छै जे के...ओ...“ऐसा-कभी-न-हो”...ओ...ओकरा
            खराब लागछै, त ऊहो फेर उकरा पकैड़ के खूब पीटैछे । और तैकै बाद कहैछे जे कही “ऐसा-रोज-रोज-हो”
            ।
            
            Afterwards, yet another <objectName type="human">man</objectName>…is working in the <placeName>field</placeName>, and his <placeName>farm</placeName> has yielded good harvest. To
            the <objectName type="job">farmer</objectName> as well, all he has to say is “may-this-never-happen”, “may-this-never-happen”. In
            other words, while he…the farmer is working in the <placeName>field</placeName>, he sees that a boy is rambling
            something, that he…the lad is saying – “may-this-never-happen”…he…the <objectName type="job">farmer</objectName> feels
            miserable on hearing this, and he too catches hold of him and beats him pitilessly. And
            afterwards he counsels the lad to say “may-this-happen-everyday”.
            
            एन्हैते करैत करैत ओ <placeName>घॅर</placeName> पहुँच जायेछे, त <objectName type="time">राइत</objectName> भो जायेछे, ओ सुइत रॅहैछे । सुतैछे नऽ जे उ सबटा भूल जायेछे
            । त ओ बाद में पुछैछे…सोचैछे...हमरा सास की कहनै छलै नाम, हमरा रास्ता में त बहूते कीछ भैल, पर कीछ
            हमरा न पता य, त अपन कन्या क कहैछे - “जे तोहर मॉय जे बनैने छलो, वैह बनौ ।”
            
            In this way, he eventually reaches his <placeName>home</placeName>, and since it is already <objectName type="time">night</objectName>, so he goes to <placeName>bed</placeName>.
            When he is asleep, he forgets everything that had happened in the day. Then, he asks…he
            thinks…later on – “What was the name of the <objectName type="food">dish</objectName> my mother-in-law had mentioned to me? So 
            many things happened on the way that I can hardly remember anything.” So, he says to his <objectName type="human">wife</objectName>
            – “Whatever your mother had cooked, cook that for me.”
            
            त ओकर <objectName type="human">कन्या</objectName> के पतै न रहै जे <objectName type="human">मॉय</objectName> हमर की बनैने छलै । तो उ सोचैय, त ओकरा नऽ, अपन कन्या के जतै जे
            ओकरा रास्ता में लोग-सब मारनै रहै, से वेहे बदला अपन कन्या स लॅ लिये, खूब मारेयऽ । तखनो ओकरा नाम ने
            याद आबेछे जे हमरा कि कहने छलै ।
            
            But his wife does not know what her mother had cooked for him. This angers him; for all the
            blows he had suffered on his way, he…he vents his frustration by mercilessly beating his wife.
            Still, he is unable to remember what his <objectName type="human">mother-in-law</objectName> had mentioned to him.
            
            त पड़ोस में एकड़ा एकटा आदमी देखलके न औरत, जे बड मारैछे, तऽ ओकरा दया लागले, त ओ एलै, त उ आबेछै
            नऽ, कि कहेछे - “मॉय गे मॉय, ऐय औरत के त <objectName type="food">खिचड़ी</objectName> बना देलकै”...त...ओ...मतलब...ओकरा याद आबैछे - “जा,
            हमर सास कहलेछेलै <objectName type="food">खिचड़ी</objectName> बनबैल”, त कहैछे - “याह त हम कहै छलियै तखन स बनबै ल ।”
            
            Then, among the <objectName type="human">neighbours</objectName> who are watching him beat his <objectName type="human">wife</objectName> brutally, a <objectName type="human">man</objectName>…no…a
            <objectName type="human">woman</objectName> is kind to her, she comes to her rescue, and she arrives in their <placeName>home</placeName> and says – “Oh
            my god, you have made a <objectName type="food">khicadī</objectName>  out of her”…then…that is when…he…he remembers, “There
            you go, my <objectName type="human">mother-in-law</objectName> had said that we should cook <objectName type="food">khicadī</objectName>!” then he replies – “That is
            precisely what I have been asking her to cook."</p>
            </div1>
            ...............
            <div1 type="sp2">
               <sp who="#auidence"
            <p>“हो गया ? जाओ, जाके <objectName type="food">खिचड़ी</objectName> बना के खाना ।”
            
            “Is that all? Go on, get back, cook <objectName type="food">khicaḍī</objectName>, and eat.”
            </p>
               </div1>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
