<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p />
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <listPerson>
               <person xml:id="jha">
                  <persName>Vineeta Jha</persName>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="coralynn">
                  <persName>Coralynn Davis</persName>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="translator" />
               <person xml:id="outsidelady">
               </person>
            </listPerson>
            
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 type="story">
            <head>
               <title>Dedh Bitna</title>
               <persName type="storyteller" ref="#jha">Vineeta Jha</persName>
               <persName type="interviewer">Coralynn Davis</persName>
               <placeName>Vineeta's home</placeName>
               <date when-iso="2016-09-08"/> Maithili Folklore 1 Documented by <persName>Dr. Coralynn V. Davis</persName>
               Line-by-line Transcription and Translation by Pranav Prakash </head>
            <div2 type="sp1">
               <sp who="#jha">
                  <p>There was a <persName type="caste">Brahmin</persName>. He used to perform his <objectName type="practice">prayers</objectName> and <objectName type="practice">rituals</objectName>, and he took care of his <objectName type="animal">cow</objectName>. Whatsoever <objectName type="food">milk</objectName> was obtained from the <objectName type="animal">cow</objectName>, it was consumed by his <objectName type="relation">family</objectName>. He had a <objectName type="relation">son</objectName> who
            would get to drink her <objectName type="milk">milk</objectName>. But he was stricken by <objectName type="being">poverty</objectName>, so he was very <objectName type="being">sad</objectName>.</p>
            </sp>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="sp1">
               <sp who="#jha">
         <p>Regarding the selling of the <objectName type="food">milk</objectName> of the <objectName type="animal">cow</objectName>, he would argue, “I am a <objectName type="caste">Brahmin</objectName>, I cannot pursue any other profession of work.”</p>
               </sp>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="sp1">
               <sp who="#jha">
         <p>Meanwhile, his <objectName type="relation">son</objectName> was growing up. So, his <objectName type="relation">wife</objectName> who was preparing some <objectName type="food">chapatti</objectName> with <objectName type="food">salt</objectName> so that he may eat it after he finished his <objectName type="practices">prayers</objectName> – he was offering his daily <objectName type="practices">prayers</objectName> to <objectName>god</objectName> – expressed her concerns to him, “Eat this meal, and go sell the <objectName type="food">cow’s milk</objectName>. I have spent my life in <objectName>tattered clothes</objectName>, but our <objectName type="relation">son</objectName> is growing up, you should send him to <placeName>school</placeName>, don’t you want to do something for him?”</p>
               </sp>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="sp1">
               <sp who="#jha">
         <p>A deeply hurtful pain gripped his <objectName>body</objectName>, as he agonized over this issue, “How can I sell the <objectName type="food">cow’s milk</objectName>?” He argued with himself, “<objectName type="animal">Cows</objectName> and <objectName type="relation">mothers</objectName> are alike, how can I sell their <objectName type="food">milk</objectName>?”</p>
               </sp>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="sp1">
               <sp who="#jha">
         <p>And his <objectName type="relation">wife</objectName> insisted, “How long must I live in <objectName>tattered clothes</objectName>? Our son is growing up. How long should we suffer in <objectName type="being">poverty</objectName>? No more, we can’t go on like this. If you bring <objectName>money</objectName> by selling <objectName type="food">milk</objectName>, then much can happen for us.”</p>
               </sp>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="sp1">
               <sp who="#jha">
         <p>She gave him some <objectName type="food">milk</objectName> and said, “Go out, sell them.” Poor <objectName type="human">man</objectName>, he went out to sell <objectName type="food">some milk</objectName>. As he went out to sell the <objectName type="food">milk</objectName>, he met on the <placeName>road</placeName>…he noticed on the <placeName>road</placeName>, there was a <placeName>snake-hole</placeName> on the wayside. An aged <persName type="snake">nāg</persName> (cobra snake) was lying inside, he was so famished that his body had dried out in the <placeName>hole</placeName>. Unwilling that the <persName type="caste">brahmin</persName> was to sell off the <objectName type="food">cow’s milk</objectName>, he poured it in the hole. The starving <objectName type="animal">snake</objectName> that was lying in there drank the <objectName type="food">milk</objectName>, and he became a satiated soul, and he spat a <objectName>gemstone</objectName> for the <persName type="caste">Brahmin</persName>. After taking the <objectName>gemstone</objectName>, he returned to his <placeName>home</placeName>.</p>
               </sp>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="sp1">
               <sp who="#jha">        
         <p>When he brought back the <objectName>gem</objectName>, his <objectName type="relation">wife</objectName> spoke to him, “That <objectName type="food">milk</objectName>, if you’d care to notice, it’s after I gave that <objectName type="food">milk</objectName> to you that so many things in our <placeName>house</placeName> have turned pleasant and pretty in just one day.”</p>
               </sp>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="sp1">
               <sp who="#jha">
         <p>On the next day, he brought the <objectName>gem</objectName> to his <placeName>house</placeName>. His <objectName type="relation">wife</objectName> asked, “Did you sell the <objectName type="food">milk</objectName>?” He replied, “Yes, here, you see, this is how much the <objectName type="food">milk</objectName> did cost. I know, this <objectName>money</objectName> is not enough, but I will sell more <objectName type="food">milk</objectName> and will bring more <objectName>money</objectName>, afterwards I will get more stuff for you.”</p>
               </sp>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="sp1">
               <sp who="#jha">
         <p>She replied, “That’s fine!” He went out the other day as well. Every day he went out, and he poured it in the <placeName>snake-hole</placeName> – poured <objectName type="food">milk</objectName> in the <placeName>snake-hole</placeName>. That <objectName type="animal">snake</objectName> gradually revived and regained his health. That <objectName type="animal">old snake</objectName> who stayed in the <placeName>hole</placeName>, he began living again. And he would spit a <objectName>gemstone</objectName> to the <objectName type="caste">brahmin</objectName>, in return for his <objectName type="food">snake [milk?]</objectName>. Finally, that <objectName type="animal">snake</objectName> became very healthy and very fit.</p>
               </sp>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="sp4">
               <sp who="#outside lady">
             <p>[Have you all seen <objectName>yantra paintings</objectName> anywhere.
            <lb/>What do you mean?
            <lb/><objectName>Yantra</objectName>…?
            <lb/>No, they are after “story”. 
            <lb/>…have they seen it anywhere in <placeName>Madhubani</placeName>, that’s what I wanted to know…]
         </p>
         <p>Then he…that is…went away…then he…when he received many gems. When many gems were given to him, say, for instance, after two days, four days…ten days, when he owned many gems, then he brought many things in his home, they accumulated bags full of stuff – toys for children, fish – we abound in fishes from old times, plenty of fishes – fish, and he brought all kinds of colorful stuff. He was practically unknown in the village. Now, however, he would have tens of visitors, they would arrive at his door, and plead, “My daughter is about to get married, please loan some money to me.” Other too came to him, “We want something.” He became very prosperous and affluent. But he still did the same thing, he offered milk to the nāg. His pampering had spoilt the snake. One day he went out…somewhere to meet his relative. He spoke to his son…his wife, “I am going away, you request our dear son to give milk to the snake.”</p>
         <p>His wife had become so haughty that she replied, “What for, now why should we give him milk everyday?” 
            “There is a grove near that place, tell him to pour milk there itself.”
            “Of course not, I am not letting my son serve milk to snakes and moles. You give them drink. My son would not follow your suit.”
            Then he replied, “I have already told you that you will hand over the milk to him.”
         </p>
               </sp>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="sp1">
               <sp who="#jha">
         <p>He left for his <placeName>village</placeName>, and his <objectName type="relation">wife</objectName> got the <objectName type="animal">cow</objectName> milked, and she gave the <objectName type="food">milk</objectName> to his <objectName type="relation">son</objectName>, “My dear <objectName type="relation">son</objectName>, go out, your <objectName type="relation">father</objectName> has asked you to serve <objectName type="food">milk</objectName> to <objectName type="animal">snakes and moles</objectName>, go, pour this for them.”</p>
               </sp>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="sp1">
               <sp who="#jha">
         <p>That poor <persName type="caste">Brahmin</persName>, however, was very reluctant to go away, he still had to leave.</p>
               </sp>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="sp1">
               <sp who="#jha">
         <p>Meanwhile, when his boy went to give the <objectName type="food">milk</objectName>, as soon as he left, he hung the <objectName>milk-container</objectName> on a <objectName type="plant">tree</objectName>, and he started playing with other <objectName type="human">children</objectName>, who were all <persName type="job">shepherds</persName>, he began playing with them.</p>
               </sp>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="sp1">
               <sp who="#jha">
         <p>That <persName type="snake">nāg</persName> who used to get <objectName type="food">milk</objectName> every day, he was…then it was time for his <objectName type="food">meal</objectName>, he was thirsty. He went out time and again, he returned to his <placeName>grove</placeName>, he did not notice <objectName type="food">milk</objectName> anywhere, he came out, and went back to his <placeName>grove</placeName> again.</p>
               </sp>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="sp1">
               <sp who="#jha">
         <p>That boy remembered, “I was supposed to give <objectName type="food">milk</objectName>, pour it in the <placeName>grove</placeName>. My <objectName type="relation">father</objectName> had asked me to pour it, pour the <objectName type="food">milk</objectName>. I should get going, I should be at the <placeName>grove</placeName>.” When he was about to drop <objectName type="food">milk</objectName> in the <placeName>grove</placeName>, he saw a <objectName type="animal">snake</objectName> there.</p>
               </sp>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="sp1">
               <sp who="#jha">
         <p>How was the boy to know that his <objectName type="relation">father</objectName> had been offering <objectName type="food">milk</objectName> to this <objectName type="animal">snake</objectName>? On seeing the <objectName type="animal">snake</objectName>, the boy brought a <objectName>stick</objectName>, and he whipped a blow at him. He whipped a blow at the <objectName type="animal">snake</objectName>, the <objectName type="animal">snake</objectName> was hit on the <objectName type="bodypart">head</objectName>. As an instinctive reflex, the <objectName type="animal">snake</objectName> bit the <objectName type="bodypart">boy’s leg</objectName>. He bit the <objectName type="bodypart">boy’s leg</objectName>, the <objectName type="human">boy</objectName> passed away.</p>
               </sp>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="sp1">
               <sp who="#jha">
         <p>Afterwards when he…the <persName type="caste">brahmin</persName> arrived at <placeName>home</placeName>, his <objectName type="relation">wife</objectName> said to him, “To which <objectName type="animal">snakes and moles</objectName> had you offered to serve <objectName type="food">milk</objectName> that my son went out yesterday, and he has not yet returned?” He was anxious.</p>
               </sp>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="sp1">
               <sp who="#jha">
         <p>He said, “Let us go, and see.”</p>
               </sp>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="sp1">
               <sp who="#jha">
         <p>He went there, and he saw his <objectName type="relation">son</objectName> fallen there. He pleaded to the <persName type="snake">nāg</persName> with folded hands.</p>
               </sp>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="sp1">
               <sp who="#jha">
         <p>Then the <persName type="snake">nāg</persName> replied to him, to the <persName type="caste">brahmin</persName>,</p>
            <lg><l>“Only a friend can ever break your heart, how one craves for the <objectName type="food">milk</objectName>?</l>
            <l>You mourn the death of your <objectName type="relation">son</objectName>, I am wounded in my <objectName type="bodypart">head</objectName>.”</l></lg>
               </sp>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="sp1">
               <sp who="#jha">
         <p>We are not <objectName type="relation">friends</objectName> anymore. Your kindness spoilt me, you gave me life, you served me <objectName type="food">milk</objectName>, and I gave you <objectName>gemstones</objectName> in return, and you became haughty. You were so full of pride. You dispatched <objectName type="food">milk</objectName> through your <objectName type="relation">son</objectName>. Your <objectName type="relation">son</objectName> beat me up.</p>
               </sp>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="sp1">
               <sp who="#jha">
         <p>Now were you to offer me <objectName type="food">milk</objectName>, were you to come to me with <objectName type="food">milk</objectName>, I will come out, I will feel the pain in my <objectName type="bodypart">head</objectName>, and I will bite you. Were you to give <objectName type="food">milk</objectName> to me, you too would think, “I am serving <objectName type="milk">milk</objectName> to a <persName type="snake">nāg</persName> who killed my <objectName type="relation">son</objectName>.”</p>
               </sp>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="sp1">
               <sp who="#jha">
        <p>That’s why, once <objectName type="feeling">animosity</objectName> develops in a relationship, once should avoid being <objectName type="relation">friends</objectName> with each other. </p>
            
            <lg><l>“Only a <objectName type="relation">friend</objectName> can ever break your <objectName type="bodypart">heart</objectName>, how one craves for the <objectName type="food">milk</objectName>?</l>
            <l>You mourn the death of your <objectName type="relation">son</objectName>, I am wounded in my <objectName type="bodypart">head</objectName>.”</l></lg>
               </sp>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="sp1">
               <sp who="#jha">
        <p>As much hurt I am by the wound caused by your <objectName type="relation">son</objectName>, you are to the same degree aggrieved by the death of your <objectName type="relation">son</objectName>. Your <objectName type="bodypart">heart</objectName> is hurt, my <objectName type="bodypart">head</objectName> is wounded. Therefore, we no more share friendly relationship with each other.</p>
               </sp>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="sp1">
               <sp who="#jha">
                  <p>And, nowadays <placeName type="country">Pakistan</placeName> is doing the same to all of us.</p></sp>
            </div2>
            
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>


